A Guide to the Records of Eastern State Hospital, 1770-2009
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of Eastern State Hospital, 1770-2009
The Library of Virginia
23459; 31783; 44812; 45017 (and 36551; 36642; 36643; 36644; 36645; 36646; 36647; 36648; 36649; 36650; 36651; 36652)
40.75 cu. ft. of paper records, 201 volumes, 42 oversize folders
Eastern State Hospital
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
As of September 11, 2019, medical records will be open 125 years after the date of creation or after date closed, whichever is later. The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) requires that individually identifiable health information of a decedent be protected for 50 years following the date of death of the individual (45 CFR 164.502(f)).
Protected health information (PHI) as defined under the Privacy Regulations issued under the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA) includes, but is not limited to, personally identifiable information such as names, addresses, and social security numbers. Restricted material may include, but is not limited to: patient lists, patient admission registers, treatment registers and medical record files. Please contact Archives Research Services for further information.
Acquisition Information
Accession 23459 transferred by Mrs. Henry E. Davis, 17 October 1949.
Accession 31783 transferred by Wyolene S. Pointer, Medical Records Administrator, Eastern State Hospital, Drawer A, Williamsburg, Virginia, 27 May 1983.
Accession 44812 transferred by Michelle L. Porter, Health Information Management Department, Eastern State Hospital, 4601 Ironbound Road, Williamsburg, Virginia, 17 February 2010.
Accession 45017 transferred by Michelle L. Porter, Health Information Management Department, Eastern State Hospital, 4601 Ironbound Road, Williamsburg, Virginia, 3 June 2010.
Accessions 36551; 36642; 36643; 36644; 36645; 36646; 36647; 36648; 36649; 36650; 36651; and 36652 (Series II., Subseries B. Architectural and Engineering Plans and Drawings), were accessioned individually as part of the Library of Virginia's General Architectural Files Collection.
Alternative Form Available
Most of the records comprising Series IV., Subseries D. Correspondence, Subject Files and Ledgers (Superintendent) can also be found on microfilm (Miscellaneous reels 4083-4085). Please note that the original records have been reboxed since microfilming and the folder numbers no longer correspond to those on the film.
Historical Information
"The Publick Hospital for Persons of Insane and Disordered Minds" at Williamsburg was first proposed by Royal Governor Francis Fauquier in 1766. A committee was authorized to prepare a bill to provide for the founding of the hospital, which it did in 1769. In April 1770, architect Robert Smith was chosen to design the new hospital and an act formally establishing the hospital was passed by the General Assembly in June 1770. Construction of the hospital building in the center of Williamsburg took several years. The first patients were admitted in October 1773. The first hospital employee appointed was the keeper, who was directed to call the visiting physician as needed because there was no resident doctor on staff. The first visiting physician at the hospital was Dr. John De Sequeyra.
The Galt family of Williamsburg worked closely with the hospital for much of the first 100 years of its existence. The first keeper of the hospital was James Galt who was succeeded by William T. Galt in 1800. Dickie Galt also served as keeper during the 1830s. In 1841 Dr. John Minson Galt, II, was appointed the first hospital superintendent by an act of the General Assembly. Additionally, Dr. Galt's grandfather, Dr. John Minson Galt, and also his father, Dr. Alexander D. Galt both served as visiting physicians prior to the establishment of the superintendent position. Dr. Galt served as superintendent from 1841 until 1862 when the hospital was overtaken by Union forces during the Civil War. Dr. Galt died shortly after being forced to leave the hospital grounds.
Dr. John M. Galt, II introduced the concept of "moral management" to the Eastern Lunatic Asylum. Moral management (or "moral therapy") suggested that the roots of insanity might be emotional. Providing kindness, an aesthetically pleasing and comfortable atmosphere, exercise, and organized social activity was believed to work better for treating mental diseases than other methods such as restraints and bleedings. Dr. Galt also went against conventional beliefs when he applied for and received legislative consent to accept mentally ill slaves as patients to the hospital in 1846. However, by 1869, racial segregation was reestablished with the creation of Central Lunatic Asylum (later Central State Hospital) now located near Petersburg, Virginia.
By the 1930s the population of the hospital had outgrown its cramped quarters in downtown Williamsburg. With no room to expand, the hospital began construction on what would be called the Dunbar Extension. The land was formally known as the Dunbar Plantation and was located about three miles west of the city. Four buildings were erected in 1936, but construction plans were halted when the United States became involved in World War Two. Construction resumed in 1947 and continued for the better part of the next two decades. For many years patients were split between the two sites, but by the late 1970s all patients were housed at Dunbar. Many of the original downtown hospital buildings were demolished in the 1960s, though a recreation of the first Public Hospital building, completed in 1985, can be found on the grounds of Colonial Williamsburg.
Eastern State Hospital experienced various name changes over the years. Originally known as the Public Hospital, it also became known as Eastern Lunatic State Hospital and Eastern Lunatic Asylum. Through an act of the General Asssemby in 1894, the current name of Eastern State Hospital was established.
Scope and Content
Contains volumes and paper records dating from 1770 to 2009. The earliest material in the collection is a Court of Directors minute book, 1770-1801, though the bulk of the collection dates from the mid-nineteenth century through the twentieth century. A few sporadic records from 2000-2009 exist as well. Included in the Eastern State records are admission registers, correspondence and subject files, architectural drawings and construction files, photographs, personnel records, newsletters, news clippings, scrapbooks, publications and reports, meeting minutes, patient treatment, and financial records. Also found in this collection are many files created and maintained by Dr. John Minson Galt, II that include his essays on mental health and other topics. The records as a whole document the complex administrative and operational aspects of the hospital, and to a lesser extent, patient life at Eastern State.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Admission and Statistical Registers, 1808-1996
Series II. Buildings and Grounds Records, 1829-1996
Series III. Commitment Registers, 1911-1946
Series IV. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1791-1997
Series V. Financial Registers, 1882-1974
Series VI. History Files, 1942-1999
Series VII. Inventory and Supply Registers, 1876-1976
Series VIII. Minutes, 1770-1989
Series IX. News Clippings and Summaries, 1964-2008
Series X. Newsletters, 1948-2008
Series XI. Papers, Speeches and Lectures, 1949-1985
Series XII. Patient and Medical Treatment Records, 1841-2009
Series XIII. Personnel Records, 1907-1988
Series XIV. Photographs, 1931-2007
Series XV. Publications, 1844-2006
Series XVI. Reports, 1842-1994
Series XVII. Rules, Regulations and Procedures, 1841-1979
Series XVIII. Scrapbooks, 1946-1991
Series XIX. Theses, Dissertations and Projects, 1949-2003
Contents List
- Series I. Admission and Statistical Registers, 1808-1996., Extent: .6 cu. ft., 34 volumes. (Volume 001-033, 130, 153;, Box 01.)
  Restricted: admission and statistical registers that are less than 125 years old. Due to the presence of restricted patient information, these records may require review by an archivist and/or redaction (if it is possible) before they are served. If redaction is not possible, the register (or certain parts of it) may be closed. Death records are restricted for 50 years.
  Contains a variety of registers used for patient recordkeeping purposes. Early admission records may not actually be admission records, but more accurately described as patient censuses that were conducted periodically. Patients were added to the register alphabetically, with each alphabetical list ordered according to the admission date of the patient beginning with the earliest. These registers were added to over several years when new patients were admitted or when older patients died or were discharged. In some cases the entries are numbered, but it's unclear whether this is a true admission number. The date ranges for these volumes reflect both the range of admission dates and the years for which the particular register was used for entries. Researchers should note that considerable overlap exists between the early admission registers and that long-term patients may have entries in more than one register. Later admission registers are organized chronologically by patient admission number, which loosely correlates to admission date. The later registers do not have indices. One volume of admission histories is also included in this series and contains additional personal information about each patient upon his or her arrival at the hospital.
  Also included here are several registers of patients which are divided into three sections: a statistical tally of the number of males and females housed in the hospital for the respective years, lists of individual patient names, addresses, dates admitted and the results of the hospitalizations. These registers also contain a complete diagnostic diary on individual patients which provide the name of the patient, treatment received and the patient's response. The volume dated 1859-1861 also contains a Board report for the year 1887 that includes a narrative discussion of the operation of the hospital,patient care, a statistical breakdown of the number of patients by sex and age, and a list of patients who received clothing.
  This series also includes a list of furloughed patients, separate registers of hospital births, deaths, and discharges, cemetery burials, and several consolidated reports of changes in population. Each population report contains detailed information about patient movements in the hospital such as the number of patients admitted, died, discharged, furloughed, escaped, total number of patients, total number of ward attendants, and application statistics. Also included in these reports are handwritten notes pertaining to certain escapees, deaths, and discharges.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of register and then chronologically.
  - Admission histories, Register of, 1879-1899. (Volume 001)
  - Admissions, Register of (patient census), 1808-1871. (Volume 002)
  - Admissions, Register of (patient census), 1812-1868. (Volume 003)
  - Admissions, Register of (tabular register C), 1868-1883. (Volume 004)
  - Admissions, Register of (tabular), 1883-1903. (Volume 005)
  - Admissions, Register of. Male patients (tabular), 1903-1926. (Volume 006)
  - Admissions, Register of. Female patients (tabular), 1904-1926. (Volume 007)
  - Admissions, Register of (tabular), 1903-1944. (Volume 008)
  - Admissions, Register of (#13561-19866), 1944-1952. (Volume 009)
  - Admissions, Register of (#19867-26090), 1952-1958. (Volume 010)
  - Admissions, Register of (#26091-32311), 1958-1962. (Volume 011)
  - Admissions, Register of (#32312-38543), 1962-1965. (Volume 012)
  - Admissions, Register of (#38544-44777), 1965-1968. (Volume 013)
  - Admissions, Register of (#44778-51007), 1968-1971. (Volume 014)
  - Admissions, Register of (#51008-59286), 1971-1975. (Volume 015)
  - Admissions, Register of (#59287-68416), 1975-1979. (Volume 016)
  - Admissions, Register of (#68417-77277), 1979-1983. (Volume 017)
  - Admissions, Register of (#77278-81534), 1983-1985. (Volume 018)
  - Admissions, Register of (#81535-86015), 1985-1987. (Volume 019)
  - Admissions, Register of (#86016 - 303468-0010), 1987-1992. (Volume 020)
  - Admissions, Register of (#158961-0040 - 312696-0010), 1992-1994. (Volume 021)
  - Births, Record of, 1953-1962. (Volume 022)
  - Births, Record of, 1962-1990. (Volume 023)
  - Cemetery burials, Record of, 1901-1996. (Volume 153)
  - Deaths, Register of, 1904-1926. (Volume 024)
  - Deaths, Register of, 1927-1941. (Volume 025)
  - Discharges, Register of, 1903-1927. (Volume 026)
  - Discharges, Register of, 1927-1941. (Volume 027)
  - Furloughed patients, List of, 1896-1908. (Box 01)
  - Patient admissions and discharges, Register of, 1868-1869 (found in a volume of Court of Directors minutes). (Volume 130)
  - Patients, Register of, 1852-1853. (Volume 028)
  - Patients, Register of, 1853-1854. (Volume 029)
  - Patients, Register of, 1854-1855. (Volume 030)
  - Patients, Register of, 1856-1857. (Volume 031)
  - Patients, Register of, 1857-1858. (Volume 032)
  - Patients, Register of, 1858-1859. (Volume 033)
  - Population, Consolidated report of changes in, 1910-1918. (Box 01)
  - Population, Consolidated report of changes in, 1918-1923. (Box 01)
  - Population, Consolidated report of changes in, 1923-1928. (Box 01)
- Series II. Buildings and Grounds Records, 1829-1996., Extent: 4.95 cu. ft; 2 volumes; 42 oversize folders. (Box 02-12;, Volume 034, 091;, Map-cabinet 9 and Super Oversize: 4.)
  Access to architectural and engineering plans and drawings of current governmental buildings requires written authorization from the appropriate authority within the agency occupying the facility. See the Archives Research Services staff for further information.
  Contains loose drawings and plans as well as project files pertaining to buildings and structures at both the downtown and Dunbar locations of Eastern State Hospital.
  - Subseries A. Architectural and Engineering Plans and Drawings, 1926-1977., Extent: 1 volume; 36 oversize folders. (Volume 034;, Map-cabinet 9 and Super Oversize: 4.)
    Contains architectural and engineering plans and drawings for various buildings and structures on both the downtown and Dunbar locations of Eastern State Hospital. Also included are maps and site plans. Most of the drawings and plans pertain to the Dunbar site. These drawings were found loose and without accompanying paperwork. Researchers should note that additional drawings and plans can be found in Subseries B. Architectural and Engineering Plans and Drawings (General Architecture Files Collection) and additional information about buildings and structures may be found in Subseries C. Building Files.
    Arranged alphabetically by plan or drawing title.
    - Administration building: Electrical alterations, 1955. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Aerial map: Dunbar Site (VDOT), 1977. (Map-cabinet 4, Drawer: 12)
    - Air conditioning (buildings D4, D5, D6, D7, D8), Preliminary drawings of, 1974. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 6)
    - Air conditioning mechanical details: Buildings 32, 34, 36 (Set #7), 1968. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Alterations to building 1: Basement and foundation, first floor, elevations and window detail, sections and details, kitchen equipment, heating and ventilation, electrical, plumbing, 1963. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Alterations to building 9: Plans and details, plumbing, mechanical, electrical, 1968. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Continued treatment building 30, 1962. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Development plan for Eastern State Hospital, 1960. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Elevations and plans for Public Hospital of 1773 (restored structure), undated. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Employee room plans and drawings of single employees' building, undated; 1950. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Female tuberculosis building (Old Site) detail sheets, 1930. (Map-cabinet 4, Drawer: 12)
    - Hospital campus lay-out, 1950. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Male receiving building (Sequeyra), Plans for, 1932-1933. (Map-cabinet 4, Drawer: 12)
    - Map, City of Williamsburg, 1956. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 9)
    - Master plot plan: Continued treatment buildings 24, 25, 28, 1955. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 5)
    - Outside utilities: Buildings 1, 2, 24, 26, 29, 1956-1958. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 5)
    - Picnic and recreational center area plans, 1963. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 5)
    - Plan and profile of proposed state highway: James City County, 1956. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Plans for addition to sewage treatment plant, 1962. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Planting plan, 1960. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Profile plan (Old Site), undated. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 6)
    - Proposed alterations to building 1 (kitchen and dining hall), 1963. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Proposed and existing electric and telephone service, 1961. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Receiving and diagnostic building, Plans for, 1926. (Map-cabinet 4, Drawer: 12)
    - Recreation center plans, 1964. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 5)
    - Recreation center planting plan, 1964. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 5)
    - Remodel of first floor of building 9: Plans and details, plumbing, mechanical, electrical, 1968-1970. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Renovation of partial basement in building 27, 1970-1972. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Sewage treatment plan (Williamsburg), 1963-1964. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Site plan (Old Site, Colonial and Hospital), 1959. (Map-cabinet 4, Drawer: 12)
    - Site plan (Old Site, for insurance purposes), 1950. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 6)
    - Site plan with topography, 1945. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 3)
    - Steam distribution system, 1949. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Storage and maintenance building: Floor plan, lower level (schedule and details), 1965. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
    - Survey and drawings of buildings (Downtown site and Dunbar), 1939. (Volume 034)
    - Topographic plat (Old Site): Proposed location of Tazewell Avenue extension, 1956. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 6)
    - Topographic study of proposed recreation area, 1962. (Map-cabinet 9, Drawer: 4)
  - Subseries B. Architectural and Engineering Plans and Drawings (General Architecture Files Collection), 1829-1955., Extent: 6 oversize folders. (Map-cabinet 19 and Super Oversize: 4.)
    These oversize drawings and plans were separated from the other Eastern State material at some point in the past and were accessioned and arranged as part of the General Architectural Files Collection; particular folder numbers are indicated below as are the individual accession numbers.
    Many of the plans are composed of multiple sheets each. This series contains architectural and engineering plans and drawings for several structures on the grounds of Eastern State Hospital, such as the Montague Building, the superintendent's residence, the laundry and bakery. Researchers should note that additional drawings and plans can be found in Subseries A. Architectural and Engineering Plans and Drawings and additional information about buildings and structures may be found in Subseries C. Building Files.
    The Public Hospital at Williamsburg was constructed from 1771-1773. A third story was added in 1841. In 1885 the building (then known as the Eastern Lunatic Asylum) was destroyed by fire. In 1972, archaeologists from Colonial Williamsburg excavated the foundations. In 1979, reconstruction of the building was begun, using a detail of the 1829 drawing as a primary source of information about the structure. The rebuilt Public Hospital was opened in 1985.
    This series also includes a very early elevations and plans for the entire hospital. Hospital Keeper Dickie Gault (possibly Alexander Dickie Galt) created the drawing at the request of the Governor's office in 1829. Gault was paid out of the hospital treasury for his work. See the Journal of the House of Delegates of the Commonwealth of Virginia, Report of the Directors of the Lunatic Hospital at Williamsburg, Document No. 12, (Richmond, 1830). A copy of this document is enclosed with the drawing.
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Arcade between Cameron hall and Brower building, 1929. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 102 (Accession 36649))
    - Bakery building, 1919. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 104 (Accession 36645))
    - Concrete floors for bath and toilet rooms: Montague building, 1914. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 105 (Accession 36643))
    - Hospital building and grounds, Map of, 1929. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 101 (Accession 36652))
    - Kitchen and dining hall building, 1929-1930. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 102 (Accession 36648))
    - Laundry building, 1928. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 102 (Accession 36651))
    - Montague building, Plans for, 1902. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 105 (Accession 36644))
    - New System of floor construction: Montague building, 1935. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 105 (Accession 36642))
    - Reconstruction of toilets and bathrooms: Thompson and Montague Buildings, 1940. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 102 (Accession 36650))
    - Sprinkler layout, 1955. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 103 (Accession 36647))
    - Superintendent's residence, 1929. (Map-cabinet 19, Drawer: 15,, Folder 104 (Accession 36646))
    - The Public Hospital at Williamsburg, Virginia: Elevations and plans, 1829. (Map-cabinet 4, Drawer: 2,, Folder 118b (Accession 36651))
  - Subseries C. Building Files, 1936-1996., Extent: 4.95 cu. ft.; 1 volume. (Box 02-12;, Volume 091.)
    Contains administrative files pertaining to various building and construction projects undertaken at both the downtown and Dunbar locations of Eastern State Hospital. The files contain drawings, plans, contract and financial information, correspondence, maintenance manuals, operating instructions and other project-related documents. Most of the files pertain to projects undertaken at the Dunbar location during its initial building phase. Researchers should refer to Subseries A. Architectural and Engineering Plans and Drawings and Subseries B. Architectural and Engineering Plans and Drawings (General Architecture Files Collection) for additional information on building projects.
    Arranged alphabetically by subject or title.
    - Administration building, Addition to (preliminary drawings and specifications), 1970-1975. (Box 02, Folder 1)
    - Air conditioning, Documentation for buildings 32, 34, 36, 1969. (Box 02, Folder 2)
    - Air conditioning, Specifications for buildings 32, 34, 36, 1968-1969. (Box 02, Folder 3)
    - Appraisal, Multiple buildings, 1969. (Box 02, Folder 4)
    - Appraisal plat plans, 1969. (Box 02, Folder 5)
    - Appraisal report, 1968. (Volume 091)
    - Boiler plant, 1958-1973. (Box 02, Folder 6)
    - Boiler plant piping and equipment, Specifications and addendum #1, 1948-1949. (Box 02, Folder 7)
    - Boiler plant specifications, 1948-1951. (Box 02, Folder 8)
    - Boiler plant specifications, Addendum #1, 1957. (Box 02, Folder 9)
    - Boiler plant specifications, Addendum #3, 1957. (Box 02, Folder 10)
    - Boiler plant specifications, Coal handling system and ash handling system, 1948. (Box 03, Folder 1)
    - Boiler plant specifications, Coal handling system and ash handling system (addendum #2), 1951. (Box 03, Folder 2)
    - Boiler plant specifications, Concrete foundation piles, 1948-1951. (Box 03, Folder 3)
    - Building 1, Specifications for alterations (West Dunbar), 1964. (Box 03, Folder 4)
    - Building 9, Documentation for remodel (first floor), 1968-1970. (Box 03, Folder 5)